A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests, Series C FA312
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests, Series C
1886-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, David
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Rockefeller, John D.
Rockefeller, Winthrop
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Rockefeller family
FA312
141 Document Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; C Business Interests; D Civic Interests; E Cultural Interests; F Economic Reform Interests; G Educational Interests; H Friends and Services; I Homes; J Housing Interests; K Medical Interests; L Real Estate; M Maps and Memorabilia; N Religious Interests; O Rockefeller Boards; P Welfare - General Files; Q World Affairs; R Welfare - Youth Files; S Documents; T Public Relations; U Public Land Law Review Commission; V Greenrock; W Properties; X Costume Collection; Y Media; Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal; AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller; AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Arrangement note
The files in this series are divided into 27 sections, as follows:
Platt-LePage Aircraft Company; Airlines; American Linseed Company; American Anglo Transvaal Company; Banks; Chase Safe Deposit Company; Bright Matter; China Industries, Inc.; Collins Brown Press; Colorado Fuel & Iron Company; Companies; Everett Timber and Investment Company; Fairway Farms; Filatures et Tissages Africains; International Business Machines, Inc.; Insurance; Marion Fruit Company; Marston and Company; Minnesota Iron Mines;New Furniture; Rockefeller Brothers, Inc.; Rockefeller Center, Inc.; Rockefeller Plaza; South America and Africa; Standard Oil Companies; Turck & Co. - Special Services; United States Steel Corporation.
Scope and Contents note
The Business Interest series documents the Rockefeller Family's investments and financial involvement in a variety of industries, companies, and geographic areas, including banks, oil, iron mining, timber, railroads, Rockefeller Center, and South America.
The series contains correspondence between members of the Rockefeller family and the Family Office on the one hand, officers and employees of the various companies on the other. The correspondence concerns all manner of management, policy and financial decisions regarding the various investments.
The family members who figure most prominently in the papers are John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson Rockefeller, Laurance Rockefeller, and David Rockefeller.
There is no material in this series dated later than 1961, but members of the Rockefeller family continue to maintain an interest and investments in a number of the businesses included in this series. The files on those particular business areas are closed. There are two exceptions to this policy. The file on Rockefeller Center, Inc. and Rockefeller Plaza are open. Files containing intimate financial information about these two firms are closed. All items recommended for closing shall remain closed for fifty years from the last date in this series, which is 1961.
Related Archival Materials note
For additional information on the Colorado Fuel & Iron Company, see the Mark M. Jones Papers, also housed at the Rockefeller Archive Center.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
World War I; World War II; Philanthropy; Art; Economic development; Economic policy; Economics; Education; Education -- United States; Family planning; Federal government -- United States; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charitable contributions; Capital investments; Business enterprises, Foreign; Business; Arts; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art, Modern; Restoration and conservation; Religious institutions; State governments -- United States; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; United States; Travel; Urban renewal; Urban policy; Government policy; Folk art; Health insurance; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Public relations; Housing rehabilitation; Religion; Public welfare; Medical care; Maternal health services; Juvenile delinquency; International relations -- United States; New York (N.Y.); Medical sciences; Philanthropy -- United States; Medical research; Medical education; Civic improvement; Child welfare; Charities -- Investments; Charities; International relations; International education; International economic relations; International cooperation; Public health administration; Public policy; Prohibition; Public health; Performing arts; New York (State); Parks -- New York (State); Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; Spelman Fund; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller University; Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); China Medical Board (U.S); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller Center; Spelman family; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); International Education Board; Sealantic Fund, New York; Standard Oil Company; Davison Fund
- Platt-LePage Aircraft Company
  - Platt-LePage Aircraft Company, 1938-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Helicopter company incorporated in 1938, with Laurance S. Rockefeller one of the first stockholders. Winthrop Rockefeller also a stockholder. Difficulties in development; purchase of stock by McDonnell Aircraft; liquidation of Platt-LePage. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, Harper Woodward.
    File Plan note
    233
  - Platt-LePage Aircraft Company - Laurance S. Rockefeller Stock Notes, 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller invested $25,100 in 1938; increased investment in 1940-1941.
  - Platt-LePage Aircraft Company - Winthrop Rockefeller Investment, 1938-1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Airlines
  - Airlines - Eastern Airlines, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller a member of original organization, one of the first directors. Reports on company activity and problems; Laurance S. Rockefeller's personal interest in company. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, E. V. Rickenbacker.
    228
  - Airlines - Eastern Airlines, 1941-1959 (Box 1, Folder 0004A)
  - Airlines - Eastern Airlines - Air Terminal, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Construction of 42nd Street terminal building.
  - Airlines - Eastern Airlines - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Stock, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's investment in Eastern stock.
  - Airlines - Eastern Airlines - Winthrop Rockefeller Stock, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Sale of 200 shares.
  - Airlines - Eastern Airlines - Laurance S. Rockefeller Stock, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Airlines - Eastern Airlines - Rickenbacker, 1939-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Personal friendship between Laurance S. Rockefeller and Rickenbacker; Christmas greetings. Complaints about Eastern service. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, E. V. Rickenbacker.
    228R
  - Airlines - Eastern Airlines - Rickenbacker - American Viewpoint, 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Published Rickenbacker's account of Pacific adventure.
  - Airlines - Fairchild Engine and Airplane Corporation, 1939-1944 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller invested $10,000 in Long Island corporation. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    228.1
  - Airlines - McDonnell Aircraft Corporation, 1939-1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller invested in stock of newly organized corporation working on military aircraft, 1939; became a director, 1941. McDonnell-Laurance S. Rockefeller correspondence re bids, plans, politicking with the Defense Dept. Connection between General Electric and McDonnell Aircraft Corporation. Labor problems; relations with Eastern Airlines. Laurance S. Rockefeller 1942 resignation; rejoined board after war. Laurance S. Rockefeller objections to McDonnell Aircraft Corporation pledge to St. Louis Country Day School. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, James McDonnell, J. Lionberger Dunn, L. Williams, Harper Woodward.
    228.2
  - Airlines - McDonnell Aircraft Corporation - Stock Subscription, 1939-1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Purchase; disposal at a loss during war to avoid conflict of interest possibilities; postwar purchases; transfer of some to Rockefeller Brothers Company. David Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller 3rd stock sales.
  - Airlines - McDonnell Aircraft Corporation - Platt-LePage Merger, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Merger negotiations with helicopter company; collapse of negotiations. McDonnell's purchase of controlling interest in Platt-LePage. Correspondents include J. McDonnell, Laurance S. Rockefeller, R. B. Marston, Phillip Keebler, Winthrop Rockefeller.
    228.21
  - Airlines - McDonnell Aircraft Corporation - Platt-LePage Merger, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 0014A)
  - Airlines - McDonnell Aircraft Corporation - Aluminum House Frames, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Plans to use McDonnell Aircraft Corporation production facilities to produce pre-fabricated houses. No results here. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, W. K. Harrison, J. B. McDonnell.
    228.22
  - Airlines - Inter-American Escadrille, 1939-1942 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Designed to further Good Neighbor policy through aviation; 1941 aviation study of Latin America. Cooperation with Nelson A. Rockefeller's Coordinator office; 1942 liquidation. Laurance S. Rockefeller a director. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Franklin Field.
    228.3
  - Airlines - Inter-American Escadrille - Contributions, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller made small contributions and guaranteed a note for the Escadrille.
  - Airlines - Inter-American Escadrille - Good Will Flight, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller provided plane used on four-month tour of South America. Pilot training clubs organized; report on Latin American conditions.
  - Airlines - Cairns Corporation, 1940-1946 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Patent-holding company granting licenses to aircraft companies switched to manufacturing aircraft material. Laurance S. Rockefeller stock option, interest in one of their patented processes, guarantee of Chase loans. No interest shown after start of war. Correspondents include R. B. Barry, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John Hoffhine.
    228.4
  - Airlines - Cairns Corporation - Laurance S. Rockefeller Loans, 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Several loans guaranteed by Laurance S. Rockefeller in return for stock option; note renewed, paid off.
  - Airlines - Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences, Inc., 1939-1957 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller a director, contributor, benefactor member. Formation of Aeronautical Archives, with Laurance S. Rockefeller a member of Archives Committee; gifts by McCormick, Guggenheim, Paul Kollsman, to Archives and Institute; Laurance S. Rockefeller's letters of appreciation. Lester Gardner's resignation. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Lester D. Gardner, Arthur W. Packard, Harold McCormick, Florence Guggenheim.
    228.5
  - Airlines - Barry and Wood, 1940-1947 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Firm organized to locate manufacturing facilities for aircraft industry. Laurance S. Rockefeller small investment, no management control. Loan returned with interest. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Eric Wood.
    228.6
  - Airlines - Anderson Aircraft Corporation, 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Produced aircraft parts; Laurance S. Rockefeller interest in sheet metal bending machine; loan to corporation. Machine unsuccessful, loan written off as bad debt. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Frohman Anderson.
    228.7
  - Airlines - Anderson Aircraft Corporation - Laurance S. Rockefeller Loans, 1941-1944 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Airlines - First Flight Covers, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Collection of 1938-1939 covers for first flights of airmail into U. S. cities and various overseas flights.
    228.8
  - Airlines - E. W. Wiggins Airways, 1946-1953 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Rockefeller Brothers, Inc. investment; no management control indicated here. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Harper Woodward.
    228.10
  - Airlines - E. W. Wiggins Airways - Stock Subscriptions, 1946-1953 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Airlines - Reaction Motors, Inc., 1947-1954 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller advanced company $250,000 with stock option provision for purchase of 51% of outstanding stock. No financial or managerial developments here. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Harper Woodward.
    228.11
  - Airlines - Flight Safety Foundation, 1948-1962 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller's contributions, interest in work. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Harper Woodward.
    228.12
- American Linseed Company
  - American Linseed Company - Annual Reports, 1901-1927 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    79
  - American Linseed Company - Certificate of Incorporation, By-Laws, 1916-1926 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - American Linseed Company - Financing, 1902-1927 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    John D. Rockefeller $3,800,000 loan to company in 1901; Frederick T. Gates' reasons for John D. Rockefeller's actions. John D. Rockefeller carried Linseed, financing its grain buying through an open account on which company drew; company paid prevailing interest rates. Problem re John D. Rockefeller's income tax. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. assumed responsibility after 1920. Correspondents include Frederick T. Gates, John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Bertram Cutler, Thomas M. Debevoise.
  - American Linseed Company - The Rainbow (Magazine) (Box 4, Folder 0032A)
  - American Linseed Company - General Correspondence, 1917-1921 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    79b
  - American Linseed Company - $35,000 Bonds, 1915-1928 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Resignation of Rockefeller representatives from Board of Directors. American Linseed Company takes over Great Eastern Elevator Company; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. held bonds for company.
    79.9
  - American Linseed Company - Stock for Officials, 1917-1921 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. financed purchase of company stock for top officials as a permanent investment, upset when some officials sold for quick profit. Interesting tax angle. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Bertram Cutler, R. H. Adams.
    General note
    [Nothing in original folder]
- American Anglo Transvaal Company
  - American Anglo-Transvaal Investment Corporation, 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    David Rockefeller investment in South African manufacturing and mining concern; no development in this file. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
    252
- Banks
  - Banks - General, 1931-1961 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Request for Rockefeller deposits in various banks; offers of stock and directorships, all declined. Changes in Westchester National Bank. Adam Clayton Powell's plan for Harlem savings bank. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas M. Debevoise, David Rockefeller, Carl Siegesmund, John E. Lockwood.
    89
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney, 1915-1957 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    89.1
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney for Automobile, 1936-1944 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney, 1929-1957 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    89.2
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney - Real Estate Powers, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney - Thomas M. Debevoise to Direct Empire Mortgage Company, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney, 1943-1951 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    89.3
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney, 1943-1951 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material.
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney - Chase Bank - David Rockefeller Business, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney - Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Equitable Branch - Chase, 1934-1947 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney - Chase Bank - Winthrop Rockefeller, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney - Bank Powers, 1935-1961 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    Conditions Governing Access
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney - Bank Powers, 1935-1961 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Banks - Powers of Attorney - Bank Powers, 1935-1961 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Banks - Trust Committees, 1951-1961 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    Changing membership of committees for trusts established by John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include Thomas M. Debevoise, John E. Lockwood, Phillip Keebler.
    89.4
  - Banks - Bank of Manhattan Company, 1918-1934 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    John D. Rockefeller owned 697 shares of stock. Printed notes of meetings.
    89.B1
  - Banks - Bank Trust Company, 1903-1946 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. deposited $500,000, bought stock in new bank, at E. L. Marston's request. Consolidation with Mercantile Trust made John D. Rockefeller largest single stockholder. Rockefeller representation on Board; sale of stock. Correspondents include Bertram Cutler, John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    89.B2
  - Banks - Chase National (Chase Manhattan) Bank, 1913-1931 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. purchases of shares; Thomas M. Debevoise and Bertram Cutler made directors, Winthrop Aldrich brought in and made President. Merger with Equitable Trust. Banking problems; appeals to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. for help from depositors and investors. David Rockefeller's services in bank, Chairmanship of Board. David Rockefeller memos re Chase branches in Latin America. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas M. Debevoise, Bertram Cutler, Winthrop Aldrich, Barton P. Turnbull.
    89C
  - Banks - Chase National (Chase Manhattan) Bank, 1932-1933 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Banks - Chase National (Chase Manhattan) Bank, 1933-1934 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Banks - Chase National (Chase Manhattan) Bank, 1944-1961 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Banks - Chase Bank - Alfred C. Marks Account, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    Opening of account for John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s agent, Mr. Marks.
  - Banks - Chase Bank - Loans to the Rockefellers, 1941-1952 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, and sons' arrangements for borrowing from bank. Memo re borrowing on call through Messrs. Jesup & Lamont, compared to borrowing from bank.
  - Banks - Chase Bank - Shareholders, 1929-1930 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    Changes in bank's by-laws.